Guide to the Joseph L. Blau Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series VII: Professional Activities
  - Subseries VII.1: American Council for Learned Societies, 1953-1975
    Primarily photocopies of minutes, miscellaneous typed reports and photocopies and original correspondence in connection with the ACLS Lecture Series on the History of Religions.
    The bulk of this series is correspondence. Most of it relates to lectures which Blau delivered at Harvard, Duke and other universities in 1964 and 1965. The rest relates to a 1971 lecture series which Blau helped to arrange.
    Most of the minutes and reports relate to the financial status and publication plans of the ACLC Committee on the History of Religion.
    Minutes, correspondence and reports are arranged separately. Minutes and correspondence are arranged chronologically except that correspondence relating to the controversy surrounding the ACLS attempt to publish Thornkild Jacobsen's lectures has been segregated and filed together as the "Jacobsen matter." Other reports are unarranged.
    - (Box 25)
  - Subseries VII.2: American Society for the Study of Religion, 1959-1964
    Photocopied minutes of meetings which Blau attended as a member of the Executive Council as well as copies of memoranda notifying scholars of conferences given by the Society, which was founded as an outcome of a 1953 ACLS conference.
    Arranged chronologically by year; undated materials are filed after this chronological sequence.
    - (Box 25)
  - Subseries VII.3: Association for Jewish Studies, 1970-1971
    Correspondence and copies of correspondence relating to the controversy surrounding a Jewish Studies appointment at Brooklyn College. Blau wrote an interim report on the matter. The material in this series is not to be examined without the permission of the Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
    - (Box 25)
  - Subseries VII.4: Society for Ethical Culture/American Ethical Union, 1941, 1952-1963
    Miscellaneous correspondence and typescripts of reports relating to the Society or to the Union, the Society's parent institution. Also includes a few photocopies of minutes of the Advisory Committee on the Institute for Ethical Studies, of which Blau was the first Director, as well as some correspondence relating to the Society's Special Fraternal Commission.
    Most of the material falls within the years 1952-1963.
    Arranged chronologically; undated materials are filed after this chronological sequence.
    - (Box 25)
  - Subseries VII.5: Conferences/Meetings, 1950-1982
    Materials from conferences and meetings in which Blau participated, including a symposium on General Education and a conference on Creationism vs. Darwinism.
    - (Box 26)
  - Subseries VII.6: Radio/Film/TV
    This series consists of one radio play, one film proposal, and one TV documentary proposal ("Sacred Journeys") for which Blau was a consultant (1980).
    - (Box 26)
- Series VIII: Miscellaneous Materials, 1912-1987
  Miscellaneous matrials relating to the life and work of Joseph Blau, and his father, Rabbi Joel Blau.
  - (Box 26)
- Series IX: Publicity, 1938-1986
  This series consists of the pages from Blau's scrapbooks containing programs and announcements of his writings and appearances, reviews of his writing, published letters in newspapers, and personal letters of thanks and congratulation from colleagues and friends. It also includes a folder of biographical data. The series serves as a good summary of Blau's professional career and noteriety.
  - (Box 27-29)
- Series X: Printed Materials
  - Subseries X.1: Journal Articles by Blau
    Copies of scholarly journals and reprints of articles wriiten by Blau.
    - (Box 30-32)
  - Subseries X.2: Books and Reprints
    About 25 books--both popular and scholarly--and a number of reprinted articles by various authors, which have been inscribed by the author or annotated by Blau.
    - (Box 33-36)